<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>DiscoverBSD Talks</title>
  <subtitle>watch - discuss - learn</subtitle>
  <id>https://talks.discoverbsd.com/</id>
  <link href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/"/>
  <link href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2016-07-03T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jan Hovancik and contributors</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Open/LibreSSL in FreeBSD</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/07/03/openssl-libressl-in-freebsd.html"/>
    <id>https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/07/03/openssl-libressl-in-freebsd.html</id>
    <published>2016-07-03T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2016-07-03T16:32:46+02:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jan Hovancik and contributors</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3 id="abstract-for-talk"&gt;Abstract for talk:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk will address the changes required to ports to deal with the changes that LibreSSL introduced (and keeps introducing). Additionally I will talk about the support-lifecycle of both the LibreSSL and OpenSSL projects and the impact on operating systems and other software projects. Lastly I will address making OpenSSL in base private and/or replacing FreeBSD's base OpenSSL with LibreSSL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Heartbleed vulnerability OpenBSD forked OpenSSL into LibreSSL. The portable version of LibreSSL was ported to FreeBSD a day after it was released causing a large number of problems with ports. Meanwhile OpenSSL changed its support-lifecycle and will stop supporting current versions very soon. LibreSSL is being actively developed which induces more changes to ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC-BSD project ran an 'EDGE' build of their packages with LibreSSL which surfaced a number of problems with major ports like Python, OpenLDAP and Apache. After the first major ports were fixed the build surfaced ca 100 packages failing to build for various reasons. I will show some examples of these problems and fixes for them. With the release of LibreSSL 2.3 came the removal of SSLv3. This caused another ca 100 ports to fail due to hard dependencies on SSLv3 methods in the libraries. Again some major ports where affected. I will show an example of this issue and the proper solution to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, there are ports that are not linking the desired OpenSSL libraries. Even when WITHOPENSSLPORTS is defined they link to the libraries in /usr/lib. Work is underway trying to make the OpenSSL libraries in base 'private' libraries. I will show the work performed and the effects on a system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="about-the-speaker-bernard-spil"&gt;About the Speaker: Bernard Spil&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read about him at https://wiki.freebsd.org/BernardSpil.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Unifying jail and package management for PC-BSD, FreeNAS and FreeBSD</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/06/19/unifying-jail-and-package-management.html"/>
    <id>https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/06/19/unifying-jail-and-package-management.html</id>
    <published>2016-06-19T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2016-07-03T16:32:46+02:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jan Hovancik and contributors</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3 id="abstract-for-talk"&gt;Abstract for talk:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically the PC-BSD project has had easy-to-use, powerful GUI utilities for package and jail management. However, being X11/Qt applications, this made their usefulness limited only to workstations, or other systems running a graphical environment, not particularly well suited for FreeNAS or a traditional FreeBSD server. With the rise of web-browser driven system management, it was also time for PC-BSD to begin converting some of its more popular tools into web-manageable forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the summer of 2014, a new project was started to re-create the AppCafe, a pkgng front-end, and the Warden, a jail manager, into web-accessible utilities for inclusion into both PC-BSD and FreeNAS. This front-end allows remote management of jails and packages on the upcoming FreeNAS 10, as well as system package management on FreeBSD and PC-BSD. This talk will provide a high-level overview of the functionality of the new AppCafe / Warden, along with technical details about the implementation for developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="about-the-speaker-kris-moore"&gt;About the Speaker: Kris Moore&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kris Moore is the founder of the PC-BSD project, and co-host of the BSDNow video podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kris Moore is the founder and lead developer of the PC-BSD project. He is also the co-host of the popular BSDNow video podcast. When not at home programming, he travels around the world giving talks and tutorials on various BSD related topics at Linux and BSD conferences alike. He currently lives in Tennessee (USA) with his wife and five children and enjoys playing bass guitar / video gaming in his (very limited) spare time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Devil in the Details - Switching to BSD from Linux</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/05/28/switching-to-bsd-from-linux.html"/>
    <id>https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/05/28/switching-to-bsd-from-linux.html</id>
    <published>2016-05-28T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2016-07-03T16:32:46+02:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jan Hovancik and contributors</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3 id="abstract-for-talk"&gt;Abstract for talk:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you mention Devils and Penguins — the mascots for both BSD and Linux, respectively — the first thing that might immediately come to mind is an NHL hockey game between New Jersey (the Devils) and Pittsburgh (the Penguins). But we’re not going there with this presentation because, for starters, it’s not a competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Free/Open Source Software users run Linux as their operating system of choice, choosing one (or more) of the 300 or so distros currently active on DistroWatch. Not as many have crossed the street, rhetorically speaking, and taken a look at the other Open Source operating system, BSD and its many variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a long time and current Linux user new to PC-BSD — essentially the BSD equivalent to Linux Mint — my intention is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;· Outline the (many) similarities and (few) differences between Linux and BSD,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;· Walk the audience through the process of moving from Linux to BSD, unless the audience is in a hurry, then I’ll run them through it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;· Describe the ease-of-use and pitfalls of day-to-day use of PC-BSD for the average user, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;· How to pitch in and make code and other contributions (e.g., documentation, translation) to BSD variants, even while doing the same for Linux distributions,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;· And more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk is more of an overview rather than instructional, though resources will be made available regarding where to download BSD variants and fundamental instructions on how to install it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="about-the-speaker-michael-dexter"&gt;About the Speaker: Michael Dexter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael has used BSD Unix systems since 1991 and wrote his first FreeBSD jail management system in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dissatisfied with existing multiplicity solutions, he has sponsored the BSD.lv sysjail and mult multiplicity research projects and took his BSD support public with the formation of BSD Fund in 2007. Michael is now the Editor of Call For Testing, a BSD technical journal and lives with his wife and daughter in Portland, Oregon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Webapps on Embedded BSD</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/05/14/webapps-on-embedded-bsd.html"/>
    <id>https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/05/14/webapps-on-embedded-bsd.html</id>
    <published>2016-05-14T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2016-07-03T16:32:46+02:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jan Hovancik and contributors</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3 id="abstract-for-talk"&gt;Abstract for talk:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Webapps on Embedded BSD And the future of FreeNAS.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Protecting FreeBSD with Secure Virtual Architecture</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/04/17/protecting-freebsd-with-secure-virtual-architecture.html"/>
    <id>https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/04/17/protecting-freebsd-with-secure-virtual-architecture.html</id>
    <published>2016-04-17T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2016-07-03T16:32:46+02:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jan Hovancik and contributors</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3 id="abstract-for-talk"&gt;Abstract for talk:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I will present our work on using the Secure Virtual Architecture (SVA) to protect FreeBSD applications and the FreeBSD kernel from security attacks. SVA is an LLVM-based infrastructure that permits us to use compiler instrumentation techniques to enforce security policies on both application and kernel code. In this talk, I will briefly describe how we used SVA to implement KCoFI: a system that enforces control-flow integrity and code segment integrity on the FreeBSD kernel to protect it from control-flow hijack attacks. I will then describe how we extended KCoFI to build Virtual Ghost. Virtual Ghost protects applications from a compromised operating system kernel. I will describe how Virtual Ghost uses compiler instrumentation to prevent the FreeBSD kernel from spying on and corrupting private application data and how it prevents the kernel from maliciously modifying application control flow (while still supporting features such as signal handlers and process creation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="about-the-speaker-john-criswell"&gt;About the Speaker: John Criswell&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Criswell is an assistant professor in the Department of Computer Science at the University of Rochester. His research interests are computer security, operating systems, and compilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Criswell is an assistant professor in the Department of Computer Science at the University of Rochester. He earned both his B.S. in Computer Science (2003) and Ph.D. in Computer Science (2014) at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John’s research interests focus on computer security and novel applications of compiler and operating system technology. John's primary research work is on the Secure Virtual Architecture (SVA). SVA enforces security policies on commodity operating system and application code via compiler instrumentation, thereby providing strong protection against sophisticated attacks. Using SVA, John built the first systems that provide strong automated memory safety protection and complete control-flow integrity enforcement to commodity operating system kernels such as Linux and FreeBSD. More recently, John has used SVA to create the Virtual Ghost system that protects application data and control-flow from a compromised operating system kernel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to joining the University of Rochester, John was a research programmer and graduate student at the University of Illinois. Before that, John worked at Argus Systems Group, Inc. John’s work at Argus Systems Group included enhancements to the AIX operating system kernel and writing utilities that utilized mandatory access controls to improve system security.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redefining the Desktop Environment for Modern Hardware</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/04/02/lumina-de.html"/>
    <id>https://talks.discoverbsd.com/2016/04/02/lumina-de.html</id>
    <published>2016-04-02T02:00:00+02:00</published>
    <updated>2016-07-03T16:32:46+02:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jan Hovancik and contributors</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3 id="abstract-for-talk"&gt;Abstract for talk:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the types of personal computers continue to increase, the traditional “desktop computer” is gradually being shifted to a smaller subset of the total systems in use. This presents a problem for open source operating systems, as the available open source graphical environments are increasingly designed for systems with powerful hardware or traditional mouse/keyboard inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open-source Lumina desktop environment is designed to solve these problems by meeting its goals of being a highly flexible and scalable interface that runs with relatively little hardware requirements. The project also provides a simple framework for integrating OS-specific functionality directly into the interface for ease-of-use without causing conflict with the underlying system or affecting portability. This session will take a top-level view of the Lumina desktop project, breaking it down to its components, explaining the framework and methodology, and listing the work that is still yet to be completed to achieve its goals.å&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="about-the-speaker-ken-moore"&gt;About the Speaker: Ken Moore&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ken Moore is one of the developers of PC-BSD and generally responsible for any graphical applications within PC-BSD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ken Moore is an avid Qt developer, and the creator of PC-BSD utilities such as the PCDM login manager, the Lumina desktop environment, EasyPBI, the device mounting utilities, and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
